RG 002:025, Prudence Crandall Statue Committee
Connecticut State Library
Prudence Crandall Statue Committee records
1961-2010
bulk 2000-2002
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. General Assembly. Prudence Crandall Statue Committee
1 cubic foot
On July 1, 2001, House Bill 6568 provided for the establishment of a committee to recommend to the Joint Committee on Legislative Management an artist to sculpt a statue of Prudence Crandall, the state heroine, for the State Capitol Building, and a location in the building for the placement of the statue.
RG002_025_PCSC
2011-027
Historical Note
In 2000, school children from Bristol, Connecticut visited their State Representative Betty Boukus as part of a field trip to the State Capitol. During the trip they learned that there was no statue in the Capitol building of Prudence Crandall, who was named state heroine in 1995. As a result of their lobbying and fundraising, with leadership from Rep. Boukus, the General Assembly passed House Bill 6568, An Act Providing for a Statue of Prudence Crandall for the State Capitol Building. This act included a provision for a $125,000 appropriation to the Joint Committee on Legislative Management for the project. Rep. Boukus served as chairman of the Prudence Crandall Statue Committee which selected Ms. Gabriel Koren of New York as the sculptor. The Committee completed its work on October 23, 2008 when the statue was dedicated in the North Lobby of the Connecticut State Capitol.
Scope and Content
The records are arranged into two series: Administrative Files and Photographs.
Series 1. Administrative Files, 1961-2010, documents the work of the committee. It is further arranged into subseries. Committee Members include committee lists and letters of invitation to prospective members. Correspondence includes letters from school children in support of the project; an undated instruction sheet for school children about how to write letters of support; letters sent with "Pennies for Prudence" donations, the fundraising program used to involve school children in the process; letters from adults regarding contributions to the project; and a letter from "The Amistad Committee, Inc." offering to serve as fiscal agent. The miscellaneous folder includes four different items which include an email from the Connecticut Valley Chapter of the Public Relations Society of America which offered to provide a pro-bono media-relations campaign for the project. Dedication contains an invitation to the dedication, a program, and notes from two of the speakers, Rep. Betty Boukus and Secretary of the State, Susan Bysiewicz. 13 color photographs from the dedication ceremony have been removed to Box 1, Folder 20. Legislative Files include testimony and letters of support for House Bill 6568: An Act Providing for a Statue of Prudence Crandall for the State Capitol Building, and background research on statues of women in other state capitol buildings. Meeting Minutes includes minutes, meeting sign-in sheets and meeting invitations. It also includes handwritten notes that are unlabeled and undated from an unknown author that may be from a meeting or general notes about the project. An audiocassette of an undated meeting has been removed to Box 2. Miscellaneous contains two items relevant to the Committee Chair, Rep. Boukus. There is a 2000 press release from when she was appointed Assistant Majority Leader of the House Democrats and an invitation to her birthday celebration/fundraiser in 2002. Press Files contain newspaper and online clippings, and press releases about the work of the Committee. Research contains information on the statue of Ella Grasso that is in the Capitol, a statue in Texas honoring school children, background research on Prudence Crandall and her school, several research papers on the students who attended her school, and the Teacher's Guide to the Prudence Crandall Museum written by the staff of the Prudence Crandall Museum to provide resource materials for teachers. Sculptor Selection Process includes correspondence and information about establishing the jury, prospective sculptors and the selection process. 9 color photographs of a proposed statue by Randall B. Nelson have been separated from this folder and placed in Box 2, Envelopes 1-9. Selected Sculptor contains correspondence from Ms. Gabriel Koren. 10 color photographs of the clay model of the final statue have been removed to Box 1, Folder 19. Statue Location includes correspondence and meeting minutes regarding the placement of the statue within the Capitol.
Series 2. Photographs, 2001, undated, consists of Ms. Koren's clay model of the final statue, the 2008 dedication ceremony, and a clay model of a proposed statue by Randall B. Nelson.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series:
Series 1. Administrative Files, 1961-2010, is further arranged into the following subseries: Committee Members, Dedication, Legislative Files, Meeting Minutes, Miscellaneous, Press Files, Research, Sculptor Selection Process, Selected Sculptor, and Statue Location. Each file is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end of the folder.
Series 2. Photographs, 2001, undated, is arranged by subject matter. The photographs of a clay model by Randall B. Nelson are group chronologically within their subject grouping. Photos submitted in January 2001 are in envelopes 1-3 and in August 2001 are in envelopes 4-9.
Related Material
, box 183, "Historical - Prudence Crandall House #47", and box 280, "Prudence Crandall", Connecticut State Library.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. General Assembly. Prudence Crandall Statue Committee.
Persons:
Boukus, Rep. Betty; Crandall, Prudence, 1803-1890; Koren, Gabriel
Subjects:
African American girls -- Education -- Connecticut -- 19th century; African American women -- Education -- Connecticut -- 19th century; Connecticut. General Assembly. Prudence Crandall Statue Committee -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut State Capitol (Hartford, Conn.); Women educators -- Connecticut -- Biography; Women heroes -- Connecticut -- Portraits; Statues -- Connecticut -- Hartford
Document Types:
Correspondence; Minutes; Invitations; Photographs; Audiocassette; Membership lists; Clippings; Bidding documents; Contract documents; Press Releases; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The records were transferred to the State Library in 2010.
Container List
- Series 1. Administrative Files, 1961-2010; bulk 2000-2002
  - Committee Members
    - Committee membership, 2001-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Constituents, 2000-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Funding, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2001-2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dedication
    - Dedication, 2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legislative Files
    - Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Research, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meeting Minutes
    - Meeting minutes, 2001-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Audiocassette of meeting, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Press Files
    - Clippings, 2001-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Press releases, 2001-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Research
    - Other statues, 1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Prudence Crandall, 1961-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Students of Prudence Crandall, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Teacher's Guide to the Prudence Crandall Museum, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sculptor Selection Process
    - Sculptor selection process, 2001-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Selected Sculptor
    - Selected Sculptor, 2002-2008 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Statue Location
    - Statue Location, 2000-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series 2. Photographs, 2001, undated
  - Clay model of Prudence Crandall by Gabriel Koren, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dedication of Prudence Crandall Statue, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sculptor selection process, clay model of Prudence Crandall by Randall B. Nelson, 2001 January (Box 2, Envelope 1-3)
  - Sculptor selection process, clay model of Prudence Crandall by Randall B. Nelson, 2001 August (Box 2, Envelope 4-9)